<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached to the natives of the city and county of Worchester in the church of St Laurence Jewry at their solemn meeting, June 28. 1681 / by George Walls ...</title>
            <author>Walls, George, 1644 or 5-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12089962</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12089962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53819</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53819)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 829:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached to the natives of the city and county of Worchester in the church of St Laurence Jewry at their solemn meeting, June 28. 1681 / by George Walls ...</title>
                  <author>Walls, George, 1644 or 5-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Samson Evans ... and Robert Kettlewell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nehemiah VIII, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53819:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53819:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached to the NATIVES Of the City and County OF WORCESTER IN THE Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>LA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RENCE JEWRY,</hi> at their SOLEMN MEETING, <hi>June</hi> 28. 1681.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE WALLS,</hi> M. A. and Student of <hi>Chriſt Church Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Samſon Evans,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Worceſter;</hi> and <hi>Robert Kettlewell,</hi> at the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Scepter,</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church, in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDC LXXXI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:53819:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53819:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Nehem. VIII. at the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Verſe.</bibl>
               <q>Go your way, eat the fat, and drink the ſweet, and ſend portions to them for whom nothing is prepar'd.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS ſolemn Aſſembly and great Meeting, as exactly anſwers and fully complies with ſome great circumſtances of this Feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles meant in my Text, in ſome of the higheſt reaſons of it's inſtitution and moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable rules for its obſervation, as if <hi>Moſes</hi> had been intereſted in the Original appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Ezra</hi> had directed us too how to keep the Feaſt. For if we conſult <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. we ſhall find it deſign'd (though there were other cauſes of its inſtitution) for the benefit of the Fatherleſs and Widow; where 'tis ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt obſerve the Feaſt of Tabernacles,—and thou ſhalt rejoyce in thy Feaſt, thou and the Stranger, and the Fatherleſs, and the Widow.</hi> And that there might juſter occaſion be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred for their rejoycing, the <hi>males were not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at this Feaſt before the Lord empty, but every man was to give as he was able, according to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53819:3"/> bleſſing of the Lord his God, which he had given him.</hi> And on the laſt day of it, which in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> is called, <hi>The great day of the Feaſt;</hi> and amongſt the Hebrews, <hi>The day of reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> from the People's being retain'd (as <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> conjectures) in order to a publick collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; there was a ſtock of money raiſed, which though ſome Learned men have appropriated to the ſervice of the Altar, and the buying in of the Sacrifices; may beſides very reaſonably be ſuppoſed meant for their ſupport alſo, to whom portions were allotted in my Text. For though their intereſt was manifeſt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, ſuppoſing it was made for no other purpoſe than Proviſion of Sacrifices, for as much as they did feaſt on theſe at ſolemn times, and were equally concern'd with others in the atonements made by them: 'tis not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, but they might have a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt and immediate ſhare in the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, eſpecially if we conſider what care they had of their Poor, as appears (among other inſtances) from the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſſeceth Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalim è verſione</hi> Joh. Wulferi, p. 132.</note> 
               <hi>ſilentûm,</hi> as 'tis rendred by a late Author, a cheſt into which devout Perſons were us'd pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to convey their Charities for the relief of Poor Children, one of which the <hi>Talmud</hi> tells us,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53819:3"/> was in every City; though ſomething of the Jew mix'd it ſelf with theſe beſt Actions of theirs: for we are there told, that only good mens Sons were to have relief thence. But if we read the foregoing part of the Chapter, we ſhall find a nearer reſemblance betwixt theſe two Feaſts ſtill; for beſides the Charitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of it, they took a care to joyn Prayers to their Alms, and the devotion was as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn as the Feaſt: <hi>For the People gather'd</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 1.</note> 
               <hi>themſelves together as one man, and ſpake to Ezra the Prieſt who ſtood upon a Pulpit of wood,</hi> as appears from the 4. verſe of the Chapter, <hi>and bleſſed the Lord the great God, and all the People anſwer'd Amen, Amen, with lifting up their hands; and they bow'd their heads and worſhip'd the Lord, with their faces to the ground.</hi> And it follows, that <hi>he read</hi> (or expounded) <hi>to them in the Book of the Law of God:</hi> that is, he pray'd and Preach'd before his Country-men at the Feaſt. The reſemblance betwixt the two Feaſts being thus ſtated, I ſhall conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The good influence and natural effects of ſuch Meetings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The advantages and uſefulneſs ſuch kind of Charities (the conſeqences of theſe meetings) have over all private ones.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53819:4"/>3. The great motives and encouragements we have to acts of charity and beneficence.</p>
            <p>1. The good influence and natural effects of ſuch Meetings.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Such Meetings give a weight and credit, revive and renew, as it were, the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, pay a reſpect, and are a kind of annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al homage to that ſo conſiderable relation of Neighbourhood, under which God choſe to repreſent men, when he propos'd them to one another as the objects of Univerſal and perfect love, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> And if the Duties of mutual love, kindneſs, aſſiſtance and good Offices, which are due to Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, were but well perform'd; all the diſorders of the world would be cur'd, and miſchiefs prevented: men would live at per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect peace, and happineſs would over-ſpread the face of the Univerſe: ſince all the harm and inconveniences men receive, are from thoſe that are near them, their Neighbours. And therefore the keeping up the Authority of this relation of Neighbourhood, is no ſmall Duty, no ordinary encouragement of vertue and preſervation of Peace. And though the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians were ſo ill natur'd, as to leave the reſt of mankind out of their Prayers; yet they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53819:4"/> could not forbear to deſire the bleſſings of Heaven on thoſe who liv'd within the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of their own Country, <hi>O</hi> Jupiter <hi>let thy rain fall upon all the good Lands of the Athenians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Love-Feaſts were the places and occaſions wherein Chriſtians in the firſt Ages of the Church, grew into one Body, one affection, one Friendſhip. And the growth and eſtabliſhment of Religion ſeems to derive much thence, for as much as ſuch Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were frequent and eaſier to be had, than other Religious Aſſemblies; becauſe they gave leſs jealouſie and ſcandal to the Heathen Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, and did not appear to have ſuch ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency towards the introducing of a new Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; Feaſting being what they themſelves practiſed, as well as the Chriſtians. And that they were to no great degree alarm'd by this Chriſtian practice, ſeems probable from the long continuance of theſe Feaſts, which we are told were in uſe till near two hundred years after Chriſt; and then too, were laid aſide upon prudential conſiderations, and only by conſent. And though corruptions and abuſes at length crept into them, and <hi>Satan came and preſented himſelf amongst the Sons of God</hi> at theſe Feaſts too, thoſe miſcarriages were the effect of their other
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53819:5"/> converſation, and theſe ſpots not contracted by, but appearing only in their Feaſts of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For the quality of ſome, and reputation of others, and the great ſecurity that ſo numerous a Body gives to it ſelf, are ſuch ſtrong Guards againſt diſorder and irregularity in ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, that the ſame cauſes that make this, on ſeveral accounts, a great, do, in ſome ſort, make it a Religious Aſſembly too. This works off the ill influences of a private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and the ſowrneſs of none at all: roots up or ſtifles thoſe ſeeds of prejudice and diſlike, that inſenſibly ſlide into our natures, corrupt our ſpirits, and darken our minds, which are equally cheriſhed by bad, or no company: maſters all theſe diſeaſes of the mind, by the powerful charms of a pleaſant, and the ſtrong diverſion of various converſation. This is the Muſick that cures the evil Spirit of every <hi>Saul</hi> among us, which the Jewiſh Scholiaſts tell us was fundamentally nothing elſe but a ſowre and diſtracted temper of mind, ariſing from the dregs of Melancholy, grief and malice; and then joy and cheerfulneſs ſeem ſo natural to, and becoming of ſuch ſolemnities, that in the Feaſt of Tabernacles <hi>the Levites ſtill'd the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 8. 11.</note> 
               <hi>that wept when they heard the words of the Law,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53819:5"/> ſaying, hold your Peace, for the day is Holy, neither be ye griev'd:</hi> as if not to rejoyce in it, were a pollution of the holineſs of the day. This gratifies and ſolaces all good natures, and ſweetens and reforms the ill; for compliance with ſuch a circumſtance of time, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of ſuiting ones ſelf to the mode and Faſhion of a Feaſt of Love, requires him to bring thither a good Humour, that hath none of his own: and the very dreſſing himſelf, though but for the occaſion, may make him like the Habit, and keep on the ſo becoming guiſe. Faſting makes men good ſolitary Chriſtians; but when they are to be moulded and cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into one Body, one Society, Feaſting moſt effectually operates towards it. Refreſhing of the Spirits with Wine, and the good things God hath given us, the mirth and rejoycing of ſuch meetings, abates the inequalities of mens minds, ſmooths the ruggedneſs of their tempers, and makes them fit to piece and fall in with each other. This is the moſt likely means to enlarge inclination, break up and lay open all ſordid encloſures of the ſoul; to take away all the baſe confinements and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our love; to give that generous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection its due latitude and liberty, not ſuffering
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53819:6"/> it to be pent up within the little compaſs of a Family, or to contract it ſelf into the narrow intereſts of Blood. For Love as other fires, the farther it ſpreads, the greater and warmer it grows; he that would ſhut up this flame, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangers to put it out. This furniſhes it with numerous objects, ſtretches it out to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of the world: a due and proper exerciſe of that love that is to become univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and a ſuitable Preface to its enlargement to all mankind. And methinks there needs no better argument of the uſefulneſs of ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick converſation and meetings as theſe, than to conſider the ill impreſſions, and dangerous conſequences of a ſolitary and Monaſtick inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; witneſs thoſe Seminaries of ill nature and miſchief, the Cloyſters; where, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with very few, and thoſe the worſt of men, themſelves; they, by being much alone, have arriv'd to ſuch ſowre and malicious tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that it becomes unſafe for the world they ſhould ever be in company: the narrow Cell becoming as frequently the hole of the Aſp, as the Retirement of the Chriſtian. But God grant we may never ſo miſtake the Prophet, become ſuch <hi>ſucking Children,</hi> ſo fooliſh as to <hi>play there,</hi> arrive to ſuch a dangerous degree
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53819:6"/> of Familiarity, as to <hi>put our hand on that Cockatrice den.</hi> Nor is that black temper of Soul (which is naturally acquir'd in thoſe retirements) more acceptable to God than 'tis to Man, as being directly oppoſite and running counter to the Goſpel ſpirit; and therefore the Jews glancing at that contempt which the Wiſe-man in <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gem. <hi>Schab.</hi> c. 2.</note> caſts upon mirth and laughter, tell us, that the Shechinah or holy Spirit reſides not with dull ſadneſs, but with due and innocent cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; and obſerve that when the minſtrel play'd, the hand of God came upon <hi>Eliſha</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings c. 3. v. 15.</note> and he propheſied; and they have a common Tradition, that <hi>Jacob</hi> propheſied not, while his grief and melancholy for the loſs of his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> remain'd on him. And we ſhall find that the great diſturbers of the World (like the more terrible and frightful appearance of thoſe that are once departed) have been ſuch, as have firſt forſaken and left it, (as they pleaſe to ſtile it.) And in one ſence they ſeem to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd and caſt it off, to diſown their intereſt in, and relation to it, in that they endeavour to deſtroy it. If a ſharp and Bloody perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution be to be carry'd on; the Covent is ſure to act a large part there; and the Moinks head or hand is always concern'd in the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53819:7"/> 
               <hi>Their Feet are ſwift to ſhed Blood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and miſery are in their ways, and the way of Peace have they not known.</hi> If unheard of Butcheries are to be acted upon the <hi>Walden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mornaeus</hi> Hiſt. Papat. p. 385.</note> the Dominicans are made the Inquiſitors, and then they are burnt alive in heaps, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the publick Records of <hi>Avignon.</hi> And <hi>Jacques Clement</hi> had poſſibly, prudently reſiſted the force of the Principles of his Bloody Religion, as ſome others do, had not the Monk been acted by the influences of his education, and by the ſame inſtitution that diſpoſes to hate ones Brother, become a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer of his Prince. <hi>Let not us therefore for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is.</hi> For beſides the ſecret Springs and movements, that, on ſuch occaſions, diſpoſe and turn our looks and hearts towards each other, and ſomewhat ariſing from the whole and Body, which the parts and members ſeem not to have brought thither, (it frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happening with men as it doth with ſome Chymical Liquors, that ferment better, and acquire nobler and more uſeful qualities by the mixture:) Beſides (I ſay) the obvious tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of ſuch Aſſemblies to continue and keep warm friendſhip, it appears a ſuitable means
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53819:7"/> of reconciliation, and begetting it where 'tis not; the method and progreſs of which may poſſibly be thus ſtated and accounted for: That the Laws of Decency and moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd Rules of Conduct at ſuch ſolemnities, require men to leave at home the rougher part of themſelves, and bring nothing with them into ſuch publick and friendly Meetings, but what is ſuitable to the ends of them, Love and Friendſhip. And though we ſhould ſuſpect that there might perhaps be ſome hypocriſy in this civility and outward ſmoothneſs; yet this too may not ſeldom make way for kinder thoughts, and be an introducement to a real good will and laſting Friendſhip. For that which keeps many men at a diſtance, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their appearing neglect of each other in their outward converſation; and they return to the eaſe and ſatisfaction of a good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as ſoon as civility and frankneſs on either ſide open but a way to it. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever believes another in earneſt, does very naturally and juſtly treat and receive him, as if he truly were ſo; which treatment ſeldom fails to make him really become what he before miſtook him for. So that the embraces that proceed only from the rules of decency and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53819:8"/> civil behaviour, may here improve into laſting kindneſs, and the Table become a ſnare only to a firm and inviolable Friendſhip. And a<note place="margin">H. Thorndike <hi>of Rel. Aſſem.</hi> c. 3.</note> Learned man is of Opinion that the reaſon why the Jews were ſo little inclinable to Idolatry after the Captivity, to which before it, they had ſuch ſtrong propenſions, that neither puniſhment nor Prophecy extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary could with-hold them from running into it, was, That after the Captivity their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues were far more numerous than before it (but that they had then ſome, appears from the 74<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Pſalm) and ſo their acceſſes to each other frequent and eaſy; and that what operated in them to the begetting ſome Love of God, ſhould yet leave that of their Brother in its former Ebb and Coldneſs, muſt not be reſolv'd into any inſufficiency in the means to unite them, but to ſome irreconcileableneſs in their tempers, and hidden cauſes, that would they ſhould longer wander and go aſtray, not yet be adopted into the Family of Love: Which brings me to ſpeak,</p>
            <p>2. Of the advantages and uſefulneſs which ſuch kind of Charities (the conſequences of theſe Meetings) have over all private ones.</p>
            <p>Now ſolemn and publick practices of any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53819:8"/> vertue have theſe two good effects above pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and ſolitary.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it recommends this vertue which they have own'd in publick more ſtrongly to every man of that Society in his private practice, and engages him more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually in obſervance of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In that it recommends it more powerfully to others.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It recommends this vertue which they have own'd in publick more ſtrongly to every man of that Society in his private practice. For beſides that the Original and firſt reaſon, all the former motives that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with any man to joyn in the publick practice, and ſolemn profeſſion of that vertue, are ſtill in force, and retain their perſwaſive efficacy; he has freſh encouragements, and new motives, from the approbation, conſent and teſtimony of all that were intereſted with him in the open acknowledgment, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtinct evidences of its laudableneſs and neceſſity: ſo that this truth is propos'd to him, not as the Opinion of a Doctor, but the Act of a Council. He has the advantage of many circumſtances to bring it home to, and root it in his memory, and as many arguments
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53819:9"/> to recommend it to his reaſon and practice. There's his own publick Act, a ſtanding Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord againſt him, if he ſhould diſown or neglect it; and his own vote for it, regiſtred to his condemnation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In that it recommends it more powerfully to others: ſuch deliberate Acts of great and conſiderable Societies, give the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, they thus ſolemnly promote, authority in the world. Virtue has always reaſon on her ſide, but faſhion and number often beat her out of countenance, and Conſcience is not always ſtout enough to bear up againſt a multitude. Though it be a thouſand witneſſes within, 'tis not always able to ſtand as many contrary examples without. Let virtue have but the protection of any number of men, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs publickly to owne, and do really practiſe her; and all is done almoſt that is needful to make her prevail in the World. The ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of mens minds, the repoſe and quiet of their Conſciences, reputation and eſteem, all vote for her: nay eaſe and Riches too are on her ſide. 'Tis almoſt only faſhion, and a cuſtom of following examples, which miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead men into vice, and miſchief that attends it. Such publick Acts therefore of virtue as are at
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53819:9"/> this Meeting perform'd, are more valued in the example, than the performance it ſelf: and what's here ſaid of all other virtues, is much more true of that leading and univerſal one, that root of all other, Charity; and they that will but return a charitable thought, for your charitable Actions, will have reaſon to think, that you who part with your money only for Duty, for Religion, for Virtues ſake, will not keep any chargeable vices (as they almoſt all are, but the oppoſite to Charity) and at a dear rate purchaſe miſery here and hereafter. Beſides, theſe ſolemn and publick Charities have this farther advantage, that in them the good man gives with greater ſecurity, and better aſſurance, that he purſues the true ends of Charity. For in private and ſolitary diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, through a too eaſie compaſſion he may believe too ſoon, or through a too ſtubborn diſtruſt he may perhaps not at all; and ſo is liable to miſtake, to the encouragement of Sin, or continuing of Miſery. Nor will the conveying it by the hands of any other ſingle perſon, alter the caſe, or remove the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience; for he has the ſame difficulties to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, and is equally liable to miſcarry with the former. And then the Caſuiſt too, does ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53819:10"/> perplex this admirable Duty, in our private executions of it, making the labour of Love ſo great, by too nicely ſtating its qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and clogging it with too Critical Rules of ſecrecy; that ſometimes the ſcruple ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows up the virtue; and by too exact a care that it ſhould not be ſeen, it becomes frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not to be felt neither: as may appear from the practice of ſome Jews, a late Writer men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">Wolferus ex Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chot Zdikin.</note> that out of a too nice regard to privacy, were us'd to drop money out of their garments for the Poor, not conſidering it might be loſt, or a rich man pick it up. But theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences are all remedi'd in our ſolemn and publick Collection; for here when Love has once open'd, there's the Wiſdom and Counſel of the whole Body, to direct and guide my hand. And whereas in private Charities, the ſhining of the good Work frequently deſtroy's it; here the light and bright appearance of it, is the excellency of the virtue. The Trumpet that always ſounds when theſe publick Alms are done, may raiſe ſome that are cold and dead, and provoke them to Love. The left hand may here know what the right does, and the World the liberality of both, and I not loſe my reward.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:53819:10"/>
            <p>Thirdly, The great motives and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we have to acts of Charity and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, and the obligations we lie under to diſtribute and ſend portions to the Poor. And this will appear if we conſider,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Advantages that ariſe to our ſelves by ſo doing.</item>
               <item>2. The Honour that is done to God.</item>
               <item>3. The benefits that accrue to our Brother.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. The Advantages that ariſe to our ſelves by ſo doing. And here we ſeem to be mov'd by all the ſprings to generous and great, or what ever may encline us to good and vertuous undertakings; and to be engag'd in the performance, by the united influence of Pleaſure, Profit, Honour and Duty. The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which is too evident, and each of them would be too tedious to be inſiſted on. I ſhall only therefore briefly mention Pleaſure and Profit. Theſe Acts of Beneficence and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, are attended with,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Pleaſure and Delight. And therefore Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> calls the charitable man a Senſualiſt. For the workings of nature are ſo ſtrong, the pangs of compaſſion ſo violent, and 'tis ſo difficult and uneaſie to <hi>hide our ſelves from our own fleſh,</hi> that <hi>to do good and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53819:11"/> to diſtribute, is a Sacrifice with which</hi> the Offerer, as well as <hi>God is,</hi> certainly, <hi>well pleas'd.</hi> The object of miſery is ſo moving, that the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of my own bowels, are ſilenc'd with as much ſatisfaction, as my Brothers are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh'd: and <hi>whilſt the Churl</hi> that ſays, <hi>Shall I</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 11.</note> 
               <hi>take my Bread and my Water and my Fleſh and give it?</hi> whilſt <hi>this cruel man troubleth his own fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 17.</note> 
               <hi>the merciful man doth good to his own Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) With Profit. For when God's pleas'd to recommend the Duty, he thinks fit to addreſs himſelf to the charitable man in terms that look like encouraging to a gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful profeſſion, rather than preſſing an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable obligation; ſtating it in words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive of the moſt direct methods of thriving and good husbandry; ſuch as lending, watering, and ſowing. And then he cannot be defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his harveſt; <hi>For though the Heaven over</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 23.</note> 
               <hi>his Head ſhould be braſs, and the Earth that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him ſhould be Iron</hi> (as we had very lately al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſeen) though the Clouds ſhould drop no fatneſs, yet <hi>the liberal Soul ſhall be fat. He ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and yet encreaſeth, hath ſow'd plentifully, and therefore ſhall reap ſo.</hi> And though God, that he may adminiſter all kind of encouragement to this Duty, is pleas'd ſometimes ſo to order
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53819:11"/> the flight of thoſe riches, the good man gives wings to, as to direct their motion to the place it began; and to convey back into their Sacks the Money of thoſe, that like <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren, lay it out in Corn, to relieve the Famine, and feed the hungry of the Land, as appears from the not failing of ſome Cruſes of Oyl, and Barrels of Meal, that ſeveral Prophets have had Cakes of, and did eat of, many daies: and frequent inſtances from Hiſtory; as the gold convey'd back to <hi>Epiphanius</hi> his Steward, and the bag of Meal that was thrown by an unknown hand into the good Widows Houſe, in the Siege of <hi>Rochel;</hi> when ſhe had not one handful left in her Barrel, that ſhe might eat with her Children and die. Though he is pleas'd ſometimes thus to reward acts of Charity, either for a declaration of his all-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, the addition of a freſh motive to vertue, or the juſtifying of his Providence to ſuch as are too apt to diſtruſt; that can allow no other recompence, but down-right pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and return almoſt in kind. It does not ſuit with the bounty of the great Benefactour (that has ſo many ways of rewarding our ſervices) to confine himſelf to this one: to ſend the good man back the very Preſent that he made
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53819:12"/> him, and make him ſuſpect he refus'd his Offering. If he ſhould think fit not to reward him with the Fruits of Corn-Fields, Olive-yards or Vineyards; he can give him a cheerful coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance without them, and <hi>put gladneſs into his heart; more than in the time when his Corn and Wine and Oyl encreas'd.</hi> There may be abundance of Peace, when there's but moderate plenty; and he may ſanctifie, when he does not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my poſſeſſions. My recompence may conſiſt in degrees, when it does not in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and when he pleaſes to contract the multitude, he may bleſs me in the greatneſs of his mercies: <hi>For there is no reſtraint to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, to ſave by many or by few.</hi> He ſometimes exchanges and gives me more ſuitable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; and I hope the kindneſs is not the leſs, becauſe he adds the bounties of his Wiſdom to thoſe of his Love. <hi>Although the Fig-tree</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not bloſſome, neither ſhall fruit be in the vines, the labour of the olive ſhall fail, and the fields ſhall yield no meat, the flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no Herd in the Stalls:</hi> though all thoſe bleſſings are deny'd me, I may be yet bleſs'd with the Prophets reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the following words, <hi>I will rejoyce in the Lord, I will joy in the God of my Salvation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:53819:12"/> Wiſdom (which is but a perfect Charity) may more liberally diſpenſe to me out of her right hand, when ſhe's ſparing with her left, and length of days may ſupply the want of ſome degrees of Riches and Honour. And this righteouſneſs or Charity (for the ſame word ſignifies them both) <hi>hath ſo much the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the life that now is, as well as that to come,</hi> that it has not only frequently been continu'd, but ſometimes miraculouſly recall'd too, for the more abſolute completion of the promiſe: for Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſays expreſly, that the force<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Gen. Homil. 55.</note> of the Alms-deeds which <hi>Dorcas</hi> did, made her capable of that great and extraordinary favour, of being reſtor'd to life. And Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> gives the very ſame reaſon why God<note place="margin">Cypr. de Op. &amp; Eleemoſ.</note> was pleas'd to honour her with this miracle. But then the charitable mans great Eſtate is in reverſion, where not only the <hi>labour of Love,</hi> but the <hi>faith that work'd by it,</hi> and always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied it, in its truſt in God, and reliance on his promiſes, will plentifully be rewarded. <hi>For he has ſow'd to the Spirit, and therefore of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit ſhall reap life everlaſting.</hi> His wiſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the unrighteous Mammon has ſtrengthned his intereſt in the other World, made him friends there, which, when he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53819:13"/> fails, will receive him into everlaſting Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. And the Fathers were ſo perſwaded of the charitable man's ſhare in thoſe many manſions, that Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> encouraging his<note place="margin">Cypr. de Mortal.</note> Brethren to die cheerfully, by an argument drawn from the bleſt Society, they would be admitted to; when he thinks fit to mention but five eminent orders of thoſe glorified ones, he aſſigns one of them to the Charitable and Merciful, and ranks them with no worſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany than the Apoſtles, Prophets, Martyrs, and Virgins.</p>
            <p>2. The Motives and encouragements we have to acts of Charity and Beneficence will appear, if we conſider the Honour that is done to God.</p>
            <p>When in compliance with his commands, we diſtribute our ſubſtance, and part with our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved treaſure, we allow his Dominion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his Authority, declare that <hi>the Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof.</hi> We magnifie his bounty and liberal proviſion for us, by thinking it ſufficient for our ſelves and others; we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg his veracity, ſhew we dare truſt him and believe him faithful that hath promiſed. And in the Apoſtolick Conſtitutions, amongſt other very ſevere Charges, the uncharitable
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53819:13"/> man is ſaid to be an Infidel, and that ſuch a one doth not believe God <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar. Conſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt. l. 4. cap. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. In the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> the Wiſe-man makes Charity the great proof and evidence of honouring God; where 'tis ſaid, <hi>He that honoureth him hath mercy on the poor.</hi> For this is in regard to their Father, to adopt his Sons, and become Guardians to his Family. This takes off all Scandal from his Providence, and reflection from his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by furniſhing them with peace and quiet, that could never reaſon themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: that are of ſo little, or dull ſenſe, that they could never ſee how good the Lord is, unleſs, in the bounty of others, they taſte it too. For narrowneſs and diſtraction of mind furniſh the Poor man with ſo few, and diſorderly, and miſery with ſo bad thoughts, that they are either too ſhort and dark to diſcover the right, and reach the foundation of Gods Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; or too corrupt and perverted, to allow the diſtinguiſhing exerciſe of it. And though more conſidering heads have ſtumbled at this, and the beſt of men had well nigh ſlipt: yet Charity herein can out-do Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and great degrees of Religion too; and, by the relief of a liberal hand, reconcile igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant heads, as well as empty bellies to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53819:14"/> acknowledgment of the good providence and bounty of the Almighty, who diſpenſes liberally to them, by the hands, and out of the portions of others. So that he who chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably gives them their dayly Bread, leads them not into this Temptation, but delivers them from Evil. And I am ſure he properly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours God with his ſubſtance, that by it breaks off his own, or prevents anothers ſins. So that there will be glory to God on high, when there is good will towards men.</p>
            <p>3. Another motive to acts of Charity and Beneficence, is, The benefit that accrues to our Brother thereby.</p>
            <p>Now though to free one from the uneaſineſs of having the keen and eager appetites of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture awak'd, and not ſatisfied; to reſcue from the ſhame of nakedneſs, and ſmart of pain, ſeems a ſufficient motive to, and worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our Charity; and the weight of the burden is not only reaſon enough to encline one that has ſenſes to deſire, but alſo him that has compaſſion to endeavour its removal: yet the beauty and true value of Beneficence, and Love then only appears, if we conſider that every inſtance of it to the Body, frequently reaches the Soul too; being uſually as ſoveraign
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53819:14"/> a remedy to the ſin of the one, as the ſufferings of the other: and therefore we find, that their converſion was the frequent effect of our Saviours kindneſs to thoſe he heal'd, and reſtor'd to their ſight; as may appear from the two blind men in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Matt.</hi> for the Text ſays, <hi>Jeſus had compaſſion on them, and touch'd their Eyes, and immediately they receiv'd their ſight and they follow'd him;</hi> as <hi>Bartimaeus</hi> did in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Mark:</hi> The miracle of mercy being to them the trueſt evidence of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and the power of God to their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. For diſtreſs and want do naturally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter the Spirit, ſower the temper, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſe the mind for God and Duty. Which probably is the reaſon, why the Hebrew Doctors (amongſt other qualifications for the reſidence of the Spirit of Prophecy) require,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſſec. Sanhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin cited by</hi> R. Albo.</note> that he on whom it reſts, ſhould be a rich and great man. For when the miſerable and calamitous Wretch has <hi>cry'd, and behold there is none to help,</hi> no charitable hand to <hi>unlooſe the heavy burthen, and let this oppreſſed go free:</hi> How is he diſpos'd to fulfil <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Prophecy<note place="margin">Iſai. 8. 21.</note> concerning the behaviour of ſome others in the like diſtreſs; and when <hi>he ſhall paſs through the land hardly beſtead and hungry,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53819:15"/> to ſret himſelf, and curſe his King, and his God, and look upwards?</hi> How enclin'd to quarrel at his Father (and perhaps queſtion his being ſo) that has beſtow'd ſo large pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonies on thoſe he is told are his Brethren, (without any kindneſs, the proof and evidence of that relation) when he is diſ-inherited? For with how unpleaſing a reliſh, muſt he feed on the husks, and how little thankful is he apt to be to him that furniſhes the coarſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, when he never <hi>ſpent</hi> any part of <hi>his ſubſtance in riotous living,</hi> and his heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary beggery forbid him ever to be the <hi>prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Son?</hi> How hard is it for one ſo early and ſo conſtantly miſerable, to lie quiet, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent in the Duſt, not to contract pollution there: for if he muſt always feed with the Swine, 'tis odds but he goes farther with them yet, and wallows in the mire; and ſo <hi>the diſtruction of the poor is his poverty.</hi> Nor will he<note place="margin">Prov. 10. 15.</note> eaſily, or ſcarce innocently, digeſt the ſcorn of this mock-ſubjection, when he is told, that <hi>all things are put under his feet, all Sheep and Oxen, and the beaſts of the field;</hi> and yet knows not how to prevail for one Fleece or Morſel, of theſe his own ſo large poſſeſſions, to warm his back or chear his Bowels. And if this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53819:15"/> Beggar that lies at the Rich man's Gate, inſtead of having his Sores lick'd and gently treated, in order to their being heal'd, ſhall meet only with the Teeth of the dogs, that ſhall tear and make them bleed afreſh; his rags and nakedneſs become more ſo, by the rough handling and coarſe treatment of thoſe that ſhould have cover'd it. If this ill and deformd ſight (that Charity might have made a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanter and more delightful proſpect) ſhall be injuriouſly chas'd thence: in this bitterneſs of his Soul he may curſe God and die; and his Blood do that which the Poor man was not permitted to do, lye at the Rich mans Door. Whereas if ſome compaſſionate Soul had time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeaſonably come in to his relief, ſome merciful Ear had been open to his crys, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he repin'd into rage and exclamation. If ſome charitable hand had been reach'd out to him, it had prevented his ſinking and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ever; and had poſſibly reconcil'd him to his condition and his God together. So that our Brother may be in a ſort <hi>redeem'd with corruptible things, as Silver and Gold;</hi> and the unrighteous Mammon be a means of his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>What then remains but that we heartily
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53819:16"/> purſue the deſign and end of our coming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, call in all the motives and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that can create or maintain Love. That there <hi>be no root in us bearing gall, and that all bitterneſs be put away. That Ephraim envy not Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, nor Judah vex Ephraim;</hi> but that what St. <hi>Paul</hi> commended in his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of every man may toward each other abound.</hi> Let us wear this great badge of our profeſſion, and make it the higheſt evidence of the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Religion, by giving our Hearts both to God and our Brother, for 'tis his right alſo. And after the wonderful Union of God and man, let not that of one man with another be unuſual or ſurprizing, let Love as well as Faith have its myſteries, and as here three, ſo let there many become one. And ſince no one thinks it ſafe to let his laſt Sun go down upon his wrath, how many ſoever he has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently ſuffer'd to ſet ſo; if we muſt die Friends, why don't we live ſo? If my laſt affections will, and muſt then embrace my Brothers hand, when the ſtrong convulſions of mine, can hardly let it go? if that be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſupport me, when my <hi>Feet</hi> are <hi>ſtumbling on the dark mountaions,</hi> and the entrance of the Grave, Why do I take hold on it ſo late? Why
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53819:16"/> ſhould my heart and affections be diſpos'd of like my Goods and Eſtate, and my Love that would be ſo much more acceptable to God, and uſeful to my Brother, in a gift, be reſerv'd for a Legacy.</p>
            <p>And if the being born within ſuch a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of ground, be a reaſon (as really it is) for men to enter into a more intimate Society and converſation one with another; how much more reaſon have they to unite, who are not only born in the ſame Country, but have one common Intereſt (as all true Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-men have) both of Laws and Religion? And therefore we have now the ſtrongeſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to become as one man, and with uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hearts bear up againſt the common danger, that threatens us, both from the unwearied contrivances and deſigns of the Papiſt, and the growing greatneſs of any ambitious Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Neighbours. Nor ſhould diſtances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Proteſtants, that differ in leſſer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, make them diſown one another in this common concern; more than being born in different Pariſhes, or at ſome miles diſtance, makes any one loſe the priviledg of this friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Society of <hi>Worceſter-ſhire</hi> men, or cauſes any unkind diviſions amongſt you. And if <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> were contented to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53819:17"/> become Friends, in order to ſtrengthen themſelves to effect no better a purpoſe of theirs, than the Crucifixion of Chriſt; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks we that are Members of the ſame Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, might imitate the prudence, though not the guilt of their policy; and joyn forces in the juſt, and quite contrary deſign of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his pretended Vicar, who threatens us with Fire and Faggot. And did not a greater degree of perverſeneſs rule us in our Religious Intereſts, than does in our Civil; we might as eaſily unite (notwithſtanding our differences in Opinion) againſt the diſturbers of our common Peace, and the Enemies of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as we do againſt thoſe of our Trade. Nor is it improbable, but joyning together againſt theſe troublers of the World, may tend to a better compoſure amongſt our ſelves, as fellow Souldiers frequently become true and laſting friends. Were the Sea breaking in upon us, men who lay within the reach of the danger, would ceaſe to purſue their private differences and leſſer quarrels, and all joyn to keep out the common inundation. Popery has as little mercy as the Sea, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may look ſmooth, and ſeem gentle as the yielding Water; where it prevails it ſwallows all. In this deluge, none of us ſhall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53819:17"/> be thought the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> but off-ſprings of the accurſed Race: a Heretick is a beaſt too unclean to have any place in their Ark. And if ſo different Nations, and that underſtood not one another, made no mutiny in <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> Army; but readily fell in with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in order to humble the pride, and chaſtiſe the inſolence of old <hi>Rome,</hi> (which was yet far more tolerable and leſs oppreſſive than that of the new) methinks our Brethren that ſpeak almoſt the ſame language with us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, ſhould find no difficulty to joyn our Army in order to a mutual defence: and that there ſhould no <hi>Hanno</hi>'s be in our <hi>Carthage</hi> to keep back our ſupplies, and hinder the ſucceſs of our Battels. And ſince the <hi>Ephramites</hi> were ſo highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd,<note place="margin">Judg. 12. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> at their not being called in by <hi>Jephtha,</hi> in his Expedition againſt the Children of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> and were ſo ambitious of aſſiſting in the War againſt that Idolatrous Nation, that they reſolv'd to burn his Houſe, that rob'd them of the Glory of fighting this Battle of the Lord: 'twere to be wiſh'd, that our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren would ſo far imitate their Zeal, as to accept our invitation to unite with us, againſt the no leſs abominable Idolatries of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53819:18"/>
            <p>Let us therefore invite the Almighty's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, by ſhewing our willingneſs not to be deſtroy'd, and our readineſs to ſave each other. Let the circulation of love and friendſhip be as free in this great Body, and convey it ſelf as kindly to every part, as the Blood do's in the natural, that the extreameſt parts may be warm too. And let thoſe <hi>uncomely parts</hi> of us, the poor; deform'd through miſery and Rags, by our bounty and Charity <hi>receive more abundant come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> Then you have <hi>Solomons</hi> warrant to <hi>go</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 9.</note> 
               <hi>your way, eat your bread with joy, and drink your wine with a merry heart, for God now accepteth your works.</hi> Your feaſting need not like that of <hi>Job's</hi> Sons be aton'd by a Sacrifice, but is it ſelf an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table one. This ſanctifies your Meeting, and prepares you for the ſolemn Aſſembly of the firſt-born, hallows your rejoycing here, and compleats it hereafter; gives you a part in that new Song, which you'll be able to learn, as being of the number of thoſe that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd from the Earth. <hi>Now the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding keep your hearts and minds in the knowledg and love of God and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt; and the bleſſing of God Almighty, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt be with you all now and evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53819:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
